A Guide to the Brian McRoberts Collection of Virginia State Capitol Materials, 1994-2002
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Brian McRoberts Collection of Virginia State Capitol Materials 1994-2002
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 386
0.42 linear foot.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The McRoberts family gave the materials to Dr. Charles Brownell in December of 1995. In 2009, the papers were donated by Dr. Brownell to Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Information
Brian P. McRoberts (d. 1995) was an architectural history student at Virginia Commonwealth University. He studied early American architecture with Dr. Charles Brownell and served as his undergraduate teaching assistant (1994-1995). In the fall of 1996, he would have been the first recipient of the Bess T. Brownell Assistantship in Architectural History. However, he died unexpectedly in the fall of 1995. In honor of McRoberts' memory, Dr. Brownell dedicated the Fourth Annual VCU Architectural Symposium in the Fall of 1996 to him.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of one box of thirty folders. The papers span from 1994-1996 and include McRoberts' drawings, papers, and correspondence from his VCU career. They also include letters from Dr. Brownell and members of the McRoberts' family.
McRoberts' greatest scholarly contribution is the reconstruction of Thomas Jefferson's design for the great hall of the Virginia State Capitol. McRoberts published his drawings in the first issue of The Classicist (1995). His drawings were used in several publications by Dr. Brownell, including a book titled, The Capital of Virginia-Landmark of American Architecture (2002).
From December 1994 to June 1995, McRoberts cataloged hundreds of drawings by the architectural firm of Carneal and Johnston. However, both his written and computerized records have yet to be found. The only records that remain are several contact sheets with images of the drawings.
The papers in the collection serve as a foundation for students to conduct further research in American architecture.
Arrangement
The Brian P. McRoberts Papers are roughly organized into four categories. The first group consists of papers regarding his submission to The Classicist. The papers, organized chronologically, include letters between McRoberts and the Director of the Institute for Classical Architecture as well as ten different sets of drawings. A second group of papers are from McRoberts' academic career, including a paper written as an undergraduate student as well as fliers created while serving as an assistant to Dr. Brownell. The Johnston and Carneal images are also included in this section. The third group of papers are correspondence between Dr. Brownell and the McRoberts family, which provide insight into McRoberts as a beloved individual. A fourth category consists of a miscellaneous photocopied image and Dr. Brownell's initial guide for the McRoberts' Papers.
Contents List
- Papers for The Classicist 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - "Call for Papers Fliers, The Classicist" 1994-1996 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Letter of Submission to The Classicist December 23, 1994 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence regarding McRoberts' Submission to The Classicist January 4, 1995 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence regarding McRoberts' Submission to The Classicist January 14, 1995 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence regarding McRoberts' Submission to The Classicist: Director's Corrections to Drawings February 28, 1995 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence regarding McRoberts' Submission to The Classicist March 17, 1995 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence regarding McRoberts' Submission to The Classicist April 19, 1995 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 1 1995 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 2 1995 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 3 1995 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 4 1995 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 5 1995 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 6 1995 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 7 1995 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 8 1995 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 9 1995 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - McRoberts' Drawings for The Classicist, Set 10 1995 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Announcement of McRoberts' Article in The Classicist in Newsletter for the Prarie Avenue Workshop (no. 33) October 1995 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Information for The Classicist (no. 1) from UVA Catalog 1995 (Box-folder 1:19)
- Assistantship with Dr. Charles Brownell 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Brownell Evaluation/Notes from Student File, Robert McRoberts August 31, 1993 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Fliers Created by McRoberts during assistantship 1995 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Interview with Brownell on Richmond Drawings from 19th-century in Style Weekly January 10,1995 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - McRoberts' Drawings Published in Brownell's Article in Richmond Journal of History and Architecture Summer 1994 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Paper presented for feshman art history class titled, "Mark Rothko: From Surrealism to Abstract Classicism: Painting in the Mid-Twentieth Century" April 1994 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Program Flier for The Institute for the Study of Classical Architecture, addressed to Brian McRoberts Summer 1995 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Contact Sheet of Carneal and Johnston Drawings n.d. (Box-folder 1:26)
- Correspondence 1995-1996, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Between Dr. Charles Brownell and McRoberts Family 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Letter to McRoberts Family from John Bryan, Associate Dean of Development December 22, 2002 (Box-folder 1:28)
- Miscellaneous n.d.,1996 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, Photo-copied image of Brian McRoberts n.d. (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Original Guide to McRoberts' Papers, Created by Dr. Charles Brownell January 1, 1996 (Box-folder 1:30)